hi everybody and welcome to the rebel
wisdom podcast so it's about a month
since we did the last podcast it's been
a really busy month a lot of content new
content coming up in the channel and
there's been a kind of common theme
emerging which is the shadow what we're
going to talk about today we did this
the interview with Zen master talking
about Jordan Peterson in the shadow
which has had like been really
successful it's had about 80,000 views
and loads of comments but really
polarized people either seem to love it
or hate it which is fantastic it's a
really interesting phenomena in itself
and we did a whole series of films about
Jordan Peterson and the left and the
kind of sub title of that or the the
subtext of that was pretty much the
shadow of the left what is the left not
seeing about itself what is it not
integrating and to move forward and what
does it need to do to recover and be a
healthy part of the political dialogue
which is another really important part
of yeah that that's kind of hat what the
shadow looks like of a wider cultural
level and I guess the Zen monk is like
the personal shadow so we'll go into
that and we're also going to go through
some of the content we've got coming up
there's some stuff that I'm really
excited about they're gonna be starting
to put up next week and we already put
up quite a few extra interviews on
mostly for patrons so if you're
supporting us on patreon great you can
go to our patreon site and already view
that if not please do consider
supporting us because then you'll get
access to all of this great material and
also help us make more of the films that
hopefully you enjoy if you're watching
this I'm assuming you enjoy them and
we've also got a live event in London on
the 18th of September that we are
calling the Great Awakening I guess
we've got a few sort of new subscribers
so maybe you're not familiar with with
the kind of the theme of this channel
but we're looking at the Jordan Peterson
phenomena we're looking at the
intellectual darkweb phenomena
and the Internet as a whole as unlocking
this great intellectual awakening online
and we're gonna be taking that out into
the real world
in September the 18th of September in
Brick Lane in London and we're going to
put the details of that below the video
here yeah so talking about Jordan
Peterson and the intellectual dark web I
think a lot of the response and a lot of
the impetus for people really connecting
with that is because these conversations
are pointing out shadows in our culture
so they're pointing out the shadow of
progressive culture the shadow of the
left in particular because a big aspect
of shadow work which a few people have
also asked us about is that when we have
a shadow basically is any part of
yourself that you reject and cut off
from the rest of yourself so for example
if I said to myself I'm not an angry
person every time I had a natural anger
response I kind of suppress it and you
put it down into the basement of your
psyche and then but you don't get rid of
it because you can because it's you so
you start projecting it out into the
world and then it looks like everyone
else is angry and you're wondering well
why is everyone always a lying ground
never hangry I'm better than that and so
you're actually seeing a mirror of
yourself through other people and but
you're still acting angry you be in that
case probably passive-aggressive so that
really that is happening on a cultural
level there's a kind of hypocrisy within
the culture of not owning for example
progressive culture not being as
progressive or tolerant as it claims to
be I think was a big part of the impetus
for a lot of the conversations that are
happening now and it's there has a
hidden tribalism that it has a hidden it
is as bigoted in some ways as the things
that it's protesting against exactly
yeah and it's the same from the
individual level it's this you know this
person the person I was just describing
who suppressed their anger they are just
as angry as the angriest person they
just haven't owned it and so part of
part of shadow work is going doe Sheen
talked about this briefly with us is
that we use this in our workshop is that
the method called three to one which
works really well so first isn't it it's
the three it's like it's not me it's out
there then it's the two so you have a
dialogue with it so
kind of communicate with an aspect of
yourself in a way that's kind of
dissociated from you and then the last
stage is becoming it and that this is
that that's I think the stage that
scares people both individually and
collectively is that oh but if I if I
accept the fact that I'm angry what's to
stop me going out and murdering loads of
people and of course that's not what
happens when when you integrate the
shadow you become more whole and it's a
very specific feeling of being more
psychologically whole but also having
more self-respect
you know Peterson talks about that
actually in the interview in truth and
time of chaos it's you kind of you own
your potential for havoc and you're like
a martial artist you have control of
yourself it's not leaking out sideways
to everyone it's it's within you and on
an individual level it's totally crucial
but also in the collective level as well
yeah it's kind of that level of
integration that I think again he said
in that interview if you it's either
under your control or it has you you
have it or it has you those are the
options yeah the question is kind of how
do you find the shadow as well and in
your life it's someone that you have a
reaction that's out of proportion to the
this stimulus by that person and it's
someone who's just like oh I cannot
stand that person for whatever reason
it's usually a good sign that oh yeah
there's a part of me that I'm not owning
in that and which brings us quite nicely
onto the fact that the dosha interview
was about the shadow and created some of
the most polarizing reactions I think
I've ever seen from an interview it's
kind of equally split and I have private
messages from people as well some people
saying that's the best interview you've
ever done it's it's amazing he's so
profound and other ones saying I felt
physically ill when I watched him and
this is this is wonderful in a way it's
really fascinating to see that this one
interview could create such different
responses and then if you looked at the
comments it was exactly the same he's a
fraud he's a charlatan together with
he's like the Dalai Lama it's like this
is this is really fascinating
and I would also hope that as we kind of
move forward what we're hoping to do is
to create a kind of dialogue that moves
beyond just those reactions that
incorporates those reactions like they
they're useful that value of valuable
information to know this is how I felt
when I saw this and maybe those
reactions were right maybe is a fraud I
don't know I spend a few hours with him
I liked him I'm fascinated as to what's
what's behind these reactions but yeah
it's like can we get to a place where we
can acknowledge those reactions and then
hold them a bit lightly and say this is
how I felt when I saw this but maybe
it's saying something about me as much
as it's saying something about that
other person and obviously a youtube
comment section is pretty much the
shadow in in in Internet form and we we
get sucked into this very binary kind of
way of looking at the world do we like
this we not like this this right is this
wrong and I guess we're trying to kind
of encourage it a form of dialogue and a
way of looking at the world that goes a
little bit beyond that and says there is
this this is the reaction I had but
there's some value in it as well and
because I think even yeah that whatever
you thought of that interview I think
there's some gold in there there's some
real gold in what he was saying and I
know that you know quite a bit more than
I do about Zen and what how kind of
ironic it is that this this created the
reaction that it did yeah it's kind of
perfect in some ways because SoDo Chien
comes from Rinzai Zen which is quite a
kind of challenging form of Zen it's
like samurai Zen it's the hard core form
that uses cones so cones are like these
little logic bombs basically like
there's no such thing as time so what
does memory and the teacher would give
that to the steel what was your original
face before you were born
yes yeah or like in the end of the
interview what is the sound of one hand
clapping it's this by the way yeah we
that one we sold there's only like a
hundred more cones to go yeah and the
point of a cone is basically to destroy
the egos capacity to make sense in
then you fall you surrender so much of a
Zen is about letting go there's a lovely
phrase I think from Dogen who was a Zen
master called Zen is like opening the
hand of thought so you're grasping and
it relates to the shadow cuz you're
grasping on to identity for example in
that anger example it's like identity is
not an angry person so you're grasping
onto that and through practice you learn
how to open it up and then you realize
that there was nothing you were holding
on to so I always describe it as letting
go of holding on so how that relates to
something like the DOE Sheen interview
is that a I think it's it's great
because it kind of doesn't matter
whether doe she is like some kind of
mystic or a total fraud if you're
looking at it in terms of what can I
learn about my own reaction to this how
can I you know using it as a mirror in a
sense and also it's it's great because
people in R in zazen they tend to
challenge so like a Cohen is like a
total it's a challenge and in a lot of
the Zen stories they would give a Cohen
and the student goes off for like sorry
Japanese so it's like the certain
amounts of time it's like six months
they're sitting on the mouthing like
well there's the sound of one hand
clapping and they come back to the
master and they had this whole like
philosophical thing and the Masters like
no you're wrong off and they're
gonna get it and they go back to another
three years and then eventually like
they're like fifty years old and the
masters like old and gray and they're
like okay they give one more answer in
the masters like now you're wrong go
away you're wasting my time and then
eventually they're like oh god I give up
and then they're like yes you got it and
that's you know it's a tricky it's a
tricksters he describes himself as a
troublemaker actually doshi and it is a
troublemaker trickster form of Zen so in
a way I'm kind of surprised by the
reaction but also I'm not I'm not that
surprised in retrospect if I think about
that tradition of Zen yeah so in a way I
guess it's that he's not there to make
you feel comfortable yeah quite the
opposite and the fact that so many
people felt uncomfortable watching it is
actually quite fascinating and and also
as you said I don't know whether they're
right or the other people are I don't
know which side is right even having
spent time with him still don't know and
yeah that the kind of
yes that's another thing of Zen you know
there's a lot there's a there's a really
famous Zen phrase if if you see the
Buddha on the road kill him
you know it's it's not about another
person telling you how to live your life
it's about you finding it's kind of a
Gnostic thing you you find the wisdom
within yourself this kind of special
knowledge that is all experiential and
there's a lot of inner sovereignty that
comes with that it's interesting you
just mentioned Gnosticism because we
also put out an interview with Tim Freak
just a few days ago which yeah I found
really interesting I really liked his
framing of the Christian story and the
pagan story as being connected rather
than being being in opposition to each
other yeah it's also been a little bit
polarizing that interview between I
guess literalist interpretations of the
Bible and the more Gnostic
interpretations which are more based
around kind of what I was talking about
a moment ago direct experience of the
divine not that that doesn't exist in
Christianity but I would say that in
lots of forms of modern Christianity the
practices used don't create mystical
experiences like taking communion
doesn't give you a saw like taking acid
for example it's a really different
experience so yes it's also an
interesting debate a little bit like the
science and Christianity debate it's not
one that I think is easily solved but it
again is an opportunity for a kind of
generative discussion if people want to
have it around around their beliefs I
guess and before that we also put out
the the whole series about Jordan
Peterson the left which was kind of
subtitled the shadow of the left and my
my friend Andrew Sweeney who I'm hoping
to catch up with again soon he's done
quite a few pieces for us and writes
quite a lot about the Jordan Peterson
phenomena online and he he made this
really interesting connection which is
to the archetypal Jordan piece and talks
about the archetypal quite a lot and he
he drew the link between so on on the
right we have the tyrannical father like
the danger of the right is the
tyrannical father the
but the danger on the left is the kind
of the archetype of the devouring mother
it's the caring instinct that then goes
too far and ends up stopping the
development of our own children so it
does not allow it is so interested in
taking care of people that it doesn't
allow people to actually develop I
thought was a really interesting
archetypal framework to look at it
because that ultimately is I think the
shadow of the left yeah and I wonder if
even that archetype contains a shadow
within it it's like the for me the
devouring mother has a sense of well why
why is an archetype dark or why is it
unresolved like in literature it's
usually because there is some ego issue
with that character that that's why
they're the bad guy like Macbeth has a
lust for power and that's his fatal flaw
there they all have a fatal flaw and I
wonder if in a way that the fatal flaw
within that devouring mother archetype
is that is trying to resolve its own
issues through the outside it's like if
I care my mother and care so much then I
will be whole in some way there's for me
there feels like there's a projection in
that as well and that's something I
noticed some often in what people would
call I guess the regressive left it's
like like I care deeply about other
people and I'm so I'm so passionate I'm
so compassionate but actually that
compassion comes with a weird edge or
there's something required for it it's
not given freely and lovingly it's it's
got a kind of edge to it it's also a
kind of tribal compassion yeah because
it assumes that other people don't have
compassion whereas when you look at sort
of politics a bit more open-minded Lee
you see that often there's no sort of
division between the amount of
compassion that's felt like on the right
compassion is generally focused mostly
on the family and then the the immediate
community in the nation-state
whereas on the left it's sort of more
Universal compassion and I think it's
wrong to see any one of those as more
advanced than any other because
I think the mistake on the left is to
assume that the it confuses rights and
responsibilities because we we may have
we may all have universal human rights
and all be deserving of love and respect
and it doesn't necessarily follow that
we have equal responsibilities to
everybody and the responsibilities in
any practical sense can only ripple out
from our immediate communities into the
into the wider world and I don't think
my mom is the best mom in the world
because I think she's superior to all
other people but I think that because
she's my mom and that's the relationship
I have with my mom and everyone should
feel like that about their mom
I mean there's a real category error on
the left when those things get confused
and that's where we start getting into
what I think of fairly crazy ideas like
we should do away with borders why the
fact that I was born in some place
should I have more rights to stuff than
than other people and then suddenly
you're into this very swamp like place
where there is no meaning there was no
meaningful attachment to place there was
no meaningful attachment to a personal
lived experience of being in a certain
place and and suddenly you're in yeah
that that's where I think the left
starts to go too far and I think that
the the shadow of tribalism on the left
saying we're not tribal but we're really
tribal I think it gets projected into
the ideology rather than the traditional
tribal matrix which would be the the
family expanding out to the tribe and
then I guess at some point it was the
nation-state but yeah so it's the
ideology and the tribe at the same time
yeah because they create an
unacknowledged tribe yes the left
creates a tribe of people who think like
us that they then refused to admit it
actually a tribe but you know if you've
ever been in those environments if you
start saying things that don't fit with
the with that worldview you will find
yourself excluded as police by language
I mean really really carefully police
but there's almost like a language a
linguistic code to it I think it's that
which is where that idea of virtue
signal name comes from which I think
people on on
well I don't know saying on the left is
a bit misleading but let's say in that
kind of environment people who aren't
fully owning their shadow I think it
really triggered by the phrase virtue
signaling it seems to be one of the
things that really gets in there and
just to return to kind of finish off
that the shadow idea is that doe Sheen
and quite a lot of the other kind of
people we've spoken to talked about
shadow work as being the essential work
for getting it out of the current
postmodern mess because the only way to
get out is for people to recognize that
they are the thing that they're
protesting against that they are
projecting out onto the world exactly
the thing that they think that they're
fighting against the tribalism the
judgmentalism the bigotry all of those
things are in some sense hardwired but
also can only be transcended and
included once they've been acknowledged
yeah that's a question of humility for
humans that like for people to have
humility and get away from this idea of
like I'm the good guy in there the bad
guys you know Carl Jung said when when
people I'm paraphrasing obviously but
when people really get down into the
shadow they realize I'm not as good a
person as I thought I was and it's just
like that simple it's like doshi and
said you have to feel really
uncomfortable that's when you know
you're really on your edge and looking
at an aspect of yourself that is so
difficult to own the shadow by
definition if it was easy just do it
like that it can take it can take years
even after identifying it to make that
leap in the 3 to 1 method to make that
leap to be like oh this is me but it's
yeah I agree with I agree with that
what he was saying it's it's what needs
to happen everywhere I think so we've
had a few people get in touch asking for
practical tips on integrating the shadow
and I think your the idea of the 3 2 1
meditation is a really good one so look
at something that triggers you in the
outside world then effectively realize
that yeah that's me yeah and we also run
workshops for men and women and shadow
work is a huge part of both of them so
for details on those check on our
website and look at the
dude helps in the show notes below we've
also got some really interesting content
now up on patreon taking this a little
while after coming back from America to
kind of edit it and get it up but we
have a really interesting discussion
between Jordan Greenhalgh and a cure of
the dawn Kara the dawn who people might
know from jbp wave and Jordan greenhalgh
who was in the glitch in the matrix film
and is one of the most yeah really
fascinating thinkers I'll play a clip of
that now and so what's happening is that
people are perceiving because it's
becoming increasingly obvious that all
of these artifacts of the way that we've
gone about doing civilization in all the
different ways like pick your poison is
really matter because they're all kind
of tied together are breaking down and
failing in a way that is no longer easy
to pretend isn't happening and so as a
consequence this triggers a deep
visceral sense and that's a good thing
right because that deep visceral sense
is the return to the aluminum the return
to the mystery the return to the the
state which by the way invokes this
conversation human beings have
encountered this problem before which
isn't in kind of an imperative for us to
transcend to the level we need to get to
to become the species that we could be
you need those kind of stakes who's it
for hmm I like that in that direction
and another new film called
understanding the intellectual dark web
with the two philosophers from the CIA
is entering just entering into the
underworld and it's a descent right it's
the ditz the mythic descent into the
underworld it's the dissolution it's
we're feeling everything starting to
shake and and buckle and it's like
fractally all these lines of division
it's like the center cannot hold
and another few films up there including
the behind the scenes with Jordan
Peterson from a interview with him last
year so yeah we're starting to do a kind
of twin track of content we'll keep
releasing stuff on the main YouTube
channel but we're going to increasingly
put up early content or exclusive
content for patrons so if you enjoy the
content and you want to help support it
please do and you'll get access to all
of this page for any content as well
yeah and also if anyone wants to join
the conversation at the wider
conversation we
have a pretty thriving discord chat
going we'll put the link to it under
here there's also now patron only
discord to discuss the content that's up
there on patreon but then also to ask
questions for the QA but either way I
think join the discord if you want to
kind of have a really engaging
discussion it's yeah it is constantly
interesting and lots of announcements
this week we have our first live event
to talk about a lot of the ideas that
we've raised in our films in London on
the 18th of September again we'll put
the details for it below the video in
the show notes and yeah do come along if
you're in London don't fly over for it's
probably only that good if I ever pretty
fly over or if you're in America it's
gonna be that good and yeah see you soon